Let us just present some very interesting, very simple and very
我们来讲解一些
interesting at the same time, properties of mean filtering,
非常简单而有趣的均值滤波(Mean filtering)的性质
basically local averaging. Let's go right ahead into that.
也就是局部平均(local averaging) 我们这就开始吧
So you see here the title Averaging, Gaussian Filter, and Heat Flow and we're
大家看到这个标题 “取平均 高斯滤波(Gaussian Filter) 和热流(Heat Flow)”
going to explain all of them. But let's just start with something very
我们会一一进行解释 不过我们首先从
simple with a very simple exercise. Let's assume I give you three numbers,
一个很简单的练习讲起 假设我给你三个数字
1, 2,
1 2
and 3. And I'm asking you the following
和3 然后我要提这样一个问题
question. I'm asking you to find the number a, such
我需要你找到一个数字a
that (a - 1)^2 + (a. - 2)^2 + (a - 3)^2 is as small as
使(a -1)^2 + (a - 2)^2 + (a - 3)^2取得其最小值
possible. Find that number.
找到这个数字
And, I'm going to basically ask you, if you need to do a lot of computations, I'm
如果你需要进行大量计算的话
going to ask you to say, no, I don't know how to do these fast.
我希望你回答我说 不 我不知道怎样迅速解决它
So, you're basically going to have the following options to say, no, I don't
也就是说 你可以选择说
know how to do that immediately or fast or yes, and then it's. So one is going to
不 我不知道怎样即刻或快速解决它 或回答是的我知道 所以否是一个选项
be no, there is going to be yes if you know how
如果你知道怎么快速解决它的话 是也是一个选项
to do it very fast. Very fast, I mean in your head with basically no pencil,
我的非常快速指的是 你只是心算 而不进行笔算或其他什么运算
nothing. You can say, yes 0, yes 2,
你可以选择 是 a为0 是 a为2
yes 4. Okay?
和 是 a为4
Let's see if you know the answer to that. Okay.
来看一下你知不知道答案 好的
Let's explain. The answer is 2.
我们来解释一下吧 答案是2
How do I know that? Because it's the average of these three
我怎么解出来的？ 因为这是这三个数字的平均数
numbers. The smallest number that will minimize
能使这个求和等式取最小值的数字
this sum is the average of these numbers. This is a very interesting property that
是这三个数的平均数 这是个很有趣的性质
in general reads as follows. if I give you a set of numbers which are, let's
它通常被表述如下 给定一组数
call them ai, a sub i, and I'm asking you to find the number a, such that the sum
称它们为ai a下标i 求数字a
for every i of (a - ai)^2 is as small as possible.
使在i取所有值时 (a-ai)^2的总和为最小值
The result of this is the average of a. So, the number I'm looking is the average
这个式子的结果是a的平均值 所以我要找的这个数字
of all the numbers that I have. So you basically sum all the numbers and
就是我所有数字的平均值 所以你只需将所有数字求和
divide by the total number of ai's that you have.
除以ai的个数
It's actually not very hard to prove that if you remember some of your calculus,
这其实不难证明 如果你对微积分还有些印象
very early calculus. So you basically define this as a n and
非常初级的微积分 你把它定义为N
you take the derivative of these, with respect to a.
并对a进行求导
You make that derivative equal to 0. You're going to find the result is
令导数值为0 你会发现所得结果就是平均值
basically the average. So this is very interesting.
这很有意思
When we are taking in an image, let's say a 3 x 3 average and replacing
当我们处理图像时 假设是 3 x 3平均
this by the average of all the nine numbers here.
用这九个数字的平均值代替这个
What I'm actually doing is I'm replacing this pixel value by the number that
我所做的其实是用一个数字来代替这个像素值
minimizes the square error. Okay?
以最小化平方差
So this is kind of the mean square error. Remember, we talk about that when we were
这就是所谓的均方差 记住 我们在做压缩时曾说到它
doing compression. A very simple operation, once again, that
再说一次 这是个用求导就可以证明的
you can prove just by taking derivatives. So, that's one interesting characteristic
简单等式 这就是平均数的一个有趣的特征
of the mean. When we're doing image processing, we're
我们所做的图像处理
basically finding the value that replaces that.
其实就是在找能代替它的值
This is going to be very interesting. We're going to see in a few videos ahead
这就会变得很有趣 我们会在接下来的几个视频里看到
that by replacing this way of measuring the error,
如果采用其它方法来计算误差的话
we can get other substitutions of this. So this is one of the properties that are
我们能够找到它的其他替换值 这就是取平均的
very interesting of averaging. Let's look at a different property.
一个有趣的性质 我们再来看一个不同的性质
So, once again remember that what we are doing is averaging in a window.
再次强调 我们是在一个窗口中取平均
It can be 3 x 3, 5 x 5, 10 x 10. It's just a window.
它可以是 3 x 3, 5 x 5, 10 x 10 是个窗口就可以
So what we are actually doing here is convolution.
我们所做的其实是卷积
For those that have a bit of background in signal processing, that wouldn't be a
对那些有点信号处理(Signal processing)基础的同学来讲 这并不令人惊讶
surprise. But I'm going to be basically explaining
但是我会通过
at, kind of a slightly different operation for convolution.
一种略有不同的卷积运算来解释这一点
So the basic idea is, what we are doing is we are taking our image x, y and we're
我们的思路是 我们取图像(x,y)
convolving it with a filter. And, let's just convolve it with what's
并用滤波器对其进行卷积 我们用所谓的高斯滤波器
called a Gaussian filter. Just a Gaussian function that has average
进行卷积操作 就是一个均值为0 方差为某数的
0 and some variants. And, remember, a Gaussian function looks
高斯函数 记住 高斯函数的形式
something like this. Okay?
就是这样 好的
It's one of the most simple functions we know.
这是我们所知的最简单的函数之一
So that's a weighted average. So in, in a discrete fashion,
这是一个加权平均数 在离散形式下
we would basically instead of just putting 1, 1, 1 every place,
我们不让每个地方的权重都为1
we would basically replace by the weights provided by the Gaussian.
而是使用高斯函数所提供的权值
So that gives us another function which we are going to call x, y sigma, because
这样我们会得到一个叫做(x,y, sigma)的新函数
depends on the variants of the Gaussian, this function.
因为这个函数是基于高斯函数的
So we could actually take a regular average, but it's nicer, it's more
我们可以取一个普通意义上的平均 但更好 更讲究的方法是
elegant if I explain this with a Gaussian filter.
用高斯滤波来解析它
So, while we are doing this, we are doing a weighted average.
所以我们这样做的时候 就是在做加权平均
We are replacing the pixel by a weighted average around it.
我们用一个像素周围的加权平均数来取代它
That's all what we are doing. Now,
这就是我们正在做的
this function is very interesting. Once again, it's x, y sigma because
这个函数很有意思 再次强调 这里是(x, y, sigma)
depends on the variance of the Gaussian. So let's just write something interesting
是因为它基于高斯函数的方差 我们在这里写一些有趣的东西
here. You might remember what's called the heat
你可能记得所谓的热流
flow. If not, I'm going to t explain it to you.
如果不记得了 我接下来会解释一下
I'm going to just write it down and explain it to you.
我会把它写下来然后解释给大家听
So we are going to write and I'm going to use the same notations on purpose.
我们开始写了 我特意使用相同的符号
So I'm going to write that the function f, is changing in time.
我这里要写的函数f 随时间变化
So, I'm going to write the derivative is changing in time according to what's
所以我这里依据f的拉普拉斯算子(Laplacian)
called the Laplacian of f, [SOUND] which is equal to the second
对时间进行求导 它就等于
derivative of f with respect to x plus the second derivative of f with respect
f分别对x和对y的二阶导数之和
to y. So the image is changing according to the
图像依据拉普拉斯算子进行变化
Laplacian. So I basically look at the change in the
我只是观察x方向上的变化
x direction. I do the second derivative, look at the
求二阶导数 同样地 观察y方向上的变化
change in the y direction. Second derivative, so, double the change,
求该方向上的二阶导数 使变化加倍
and basically, this is the heat flow. And, if you remember some basic
这就是所谓的热流 你可能记得
properties of the heat flow, it basically talks about diffusion.
热流的性质基本都是在讲扩散
So you have heat in a room and the heat diffuses in the room.
就像是你的房间有热量 而热量在其中扩散
If everything is isotropic, nothing can stop it.
如果所有东西都是单折射性的 那什么都不会阻止它
It diffuses according to this equation. Now, why did I write this?
它们依据这个等式来扩散 为什么我写下这个呢？
Because, the Gaussian filter actually satisfies this equation.
这是因为高斯滤波满足这个等式
It's actually something very interesting and exactly actually depends on the time,
这很有趣 而且它是由时间变化决定的
so the more you let this diffuse is equivalent to having a large sigma, a
你这里扩散得更充分 就等同于有一个大的sigma 或者说一个大的方差
larger variance. So once again,
再次强调
the result of doing this local averaging with a Gaussian filtering is equivalent
用高斯滤波器进行这个局部平均所得的结果
to the result of taking the image, thinking like the pixel values, the gray
等同于把图像的像素值 灰度值想象成热量
values are heat, and let it run according to the heat flow
让它遵循着热流来运作
which is these and those are equivalent operations.
也就是遵循这个等式 这两个是等价的运算
So if I let it run for certain time, once again, the pixel values are heat.
如果我们让它运作一段时间 再讲一次 这里像素值是热量
It's running for certain time, that's equivalent to picking a certain variance
它运作一段时间 这就等同于
that depends exactly on the time and applying a Gaussian filter to the image.
选择一个完全由时间决定的方差 并对图像做高斯滤波
So the pixel values are diffusing in the same way as the heat flow is diffusing
所以像素值的扩散就像是热量基于热流的扩散
heat. Those two are basically equivalent
这两个大致相通
things. Once again, it's not very hard to prove
这也是不难证明的
that. And if you want one other interesting
如果你想再看一个有趣的练习
exercise replace f by this expression. So basically, take the derivatives, don't
可以用这个表达式代替f 就是说 我们进行求导
do the derivatives according to T, do the derivatives according to sigma.
但不是对t求导 而是对sigma求导
And here, do the derivatives according to x and to y, and you're going to find that
在这里则对x和y求导
this satisfies this equation. And that's because of derivatives are
你就会发现这满足这个等式 这是因为求导是线性的
linear, so this is a linear operation. And if you're not very familiar to how to
这是一个线性运算 如果你不清楚怎么做
do that, just consider that as an extra exercise for those that want to go a bit
就把它当做一个给那些
deeper in the math for this particular video.
想在与此视频有关的数学上稍稍深入的人的练习吧
And now, why is this interesting is because as we are going to see in a few
这个很有趣的原因是 像我们接下来几周会了解到的那样
weeks ahead. Somebody might ask, okay, now you just told me that local image
有些人可能会问 你刚才讲到
processing is related to heat flow. Maybe I can design a different equation
局部图像处理与热流有关 也许我可以设计一个与此不同的等式
here that will do other interesting things into image processing and we're
来做另外一些有趣的图像处理
going to see that that's possible. And again, that's going to be a big
我们会看到这是有可能的 一样的 它会涉及到更高等的数学知识
mathematical more advance and is going to happen in a few weeks.
接下来几周会讲到它们
So we have seen a couple if interesting properties of this local average.
那么我们已经学会了局部平均的一些有趣性质
One is that is kind of computing the means, the value that minimizes the mean
第一点 其类似于计算平均数 使一定区域内
square error in the region. And the second, that there is an
均方差取最小值 第二点是
equivalence between pixel values and heat.
像素值和热量之间有相通的地方
And what this local averaging is doing is diffusing the pixel values and that's why
所以局部平均就是在扩散像素值
also is blurring the image. If you remember, we saw that it's
这就是为什么它使图像变模糊了 如果你记得
blurring it, because it's diffusing them. And we know that, again, that happens
我们看到它使图像模糊 就是因为像素值被扩散了 我们也知道
with heat. If you start with hot in one place and
这同样适用于热量 如果在开始时 一个地方热
cold in the other, the heat flow will diffuse the heat and
而另一个地方冷 热流会使热量扩散
will become more uniform. Of course, if you wait for a long time,
使之变得更均衡 当然 如果你等足够长时间
which is equivalent to using a very large variance,
那就等价于有一个很大的方差
what we get is basically the mean value. So you are going to basically get the
那我们就会得到平均数 那就得到的就是
average in the whole image. So once again, a couple of interesting
整个图像的均值 像我们说过的那样 这就是一些
properties about the local averaging. Next, we're going to see a different type
有趣的局部平均的性质 接下来 我们会看到不同类型的局部运算
of local operation that will actually help us not to blur the edges.
它们能让我们使边缘不变模糊
See you in the next video. Thank you.
下次视频见 谢谢 // 果壳教育无边界字幕组 | leafsherry | 风过成伤 | zeadoit